Guide to the Joseph Jeremiah Lawrence Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Joseph Jeremiah Lawrence papers
1833-1902
MS 986
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1.25
(4 boxes)
Chiefly ships' logs and accounts for nine ships on which Lawrence was master between 1842 and 1865. These were engaged in the trans-Atlantic and South American trade, and the log book for the ship Hindoo also contains passenger lists with place of birth and occupation for passengers from England to the United States. Also in the papers are family account books and financial papers (1868-1902).
Lawrence, Joseph Jeremiah, -1871?
Scope and Contents
The Joseph Jeremiah Lawrence Papers consist entirely of bound volumes of ships' logs and accounts. There are abstract logs and journals for seven ships on which Lawrence served between 1845 and 1863, as well as a log book kept during 1865-1866. The financial papers include account books for six ships, a business day book and a ledger for stocks and bonds, and a family cash book. The volumes are arranged chronologically.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Joseph J. Lawrence was master of various vessels sailing between New York and Liverpool and other English ports.
Shipping -- Connecticut -- New London; New London (Conn.) -- Commerce; United States -- Emigration and immigration; Logs (records); Ships' papers; Shipmasters; Lawrence, Joseph Jeremiah, -1871?; America (Ship); Atlantic (Ship); Columbus (Ship); Cornelia (Ship); Eagle (Ship); Hindoo (Ship); Isaac Hicks (Ship); Webster (Ship)
- Inventory
  - Log book, 1865-1866 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Abstract logs and journals
    - Cornelia [journal only]
      General note
      See: Folder 9
    - Hindoo (with passenger lists), 1845-1863 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      See also: Folder 11-12
    - Hindoo, 1845-1846 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Atlantic, Columbus, and America, 1848-1851 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Webster, 1854-1857 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Webster, 1857-1860 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Webster, 1857-1860 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Webster and Eagle, 1860-1863 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Webster, 1861-1863
      See: Folder 11-12
  - Accounts
    - Day book and journal, 1833-1836 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Isaac Hicks, Hindoo, Atlantic, Columbus, America, and Webster, 1842-1863 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Ledger for stock and bond transactions, 1868-1902 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Cash book for family expenses, 1882-1893 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Oversize, 1844-1845, 1861-1862 (Box 4, Folder 11 - 12)